Edward R. Murrow Papers MS025
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Edward R. Murrow Papers
1927 -- 1965
1890 -- 1992
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Murrow, Edward R.
MS025
167.24 Linear Feet 151 oversize boxes, 144 letter size document boxes, 23 record cartons, 1 half letter size document box, 1 half legal size document box, 1 poster tube, 2 oversized folders, and 2 volumes.
1 Artifact(s)
41 Audiovisual Object(s)
931 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eight series. Series I consists of Correspondence, arranged by topic and then primarily chronological. Series II consists of Personal materials, including Murrow's family, his education, awards, publicity, personal correspondence, and papers related to his death. Series III consists of papers related to Murrow's professional life at the Institute of International Education, CBS, and USIA. Series IV contains Murrow's involvement in projects including his albums, publications, scripts, speeches, and in various clubs and organizations. Series V contains audio-visual materials from some of Murrow's radio broadcasts and television programs. Series VI consists of Murrow's memorabilia, including diaries, furnishings, honorary degrees and citations, and personal items. Series VII consists of the over 1,600 publications contained in Murrow's library, located in The Murrow Room. Series VIII contains audio-visual tributes to Edward R. Murrow. Series IX contains administrative files, reference requests and letters.
Custodial History
On December 24, 1969, Mrs. Janet H. B. Murrow, widow of Edward R. Murrow, by grant of gift, transferred title to the books, papers, scripts, tapes, films, and memorabilia deposited with the Murrow Center, to The Edward R. Murrow Center of Public Diplomacy of The Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University. These materials were Mr. Murrow's library and the file records of his professional career with some personal materials included.
This gift was accepted by the Murrow Center, subject to the following conditions: "It is my understanding that the Murrow Center will keep the aforementioned materials in the Murrow Center Library, will catalog them in the manner which will make them of maximum benefit in achieving the Center's objectives and will make them available - under appropriate regulations and in the Center's premises or library - to interested students. My son, Charles C. Murrow, and I wish to make sure that quotations and other uses of such materials in published works will reflect properly upon Mr. Murrow's memory and conform to the spirit in which this gift is being made. Therefore, during my life and during the life of my son, you shall not grant any publication rights in any of such materials (other than the right to quote short excerpts therefrom in scholarly works), unless such grant is approved by me, or if I am not living, by my son.
This gift is made subject to all rights, including common law and statutory copyright, which others may have in any of the aforementioned materials. It is also made subject to a certain agreement made as of March 16, 1966, between CBS News, a division of Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc., and the Estate of Edward R. Murrow whereby CBS News retained exclusive broadcasting rights in certain of the aforementioned materials."
December 24, 1969 (Signed) Janet H. B. Murrow December 31, 1969 (Agreed to) Tufts University, C. Russell de Burlo, Jr.
Other donations were integrated into the collection while the materials were still at the Fletcher School; some donors are unknown. Known donors include Mary Marvin Breckinridge, Joseph E. Persico, and Edward Bliss.
This collection is open, but the Murrow estate, CBS, and other entities hold the copyright. For permissions, please contact the copyright holder.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence, personal materials, work files, scripts, diaries, photographs, audiovisual materials, memorabilia, awards, books, clippings, and tributes to Murrow upon his death. Audiovisual materials include phonograph records, and film and audiotape reels of various formats. The bulk of the material dates from 1927 to 1965 and primarily documents the professional life of Edward R. Murrow. Through these materials one can trace major developments in the history of US news broadcasting, and Murrow's work for the Institute of International Education, CBS Europe and CBS USA as well as the United States Information Agency.
Correspondence comprises the bulk of Murrow's papers and includes the entire period of his career from 1930 to 1965. Please note that there is little correspondence for the period when he was Director of the United States Information Agency. Correspondence relates to historical and current issues; deal with key points and broadcasts in his career; cover problems of reporting and public diplomacy, radio and television - their role, their failures, their triumphs; reveal reactions to his work from viewers, celebrities, students, and how he handled criticism of his reporting and his view of his job; general interest items, including anecdotes, humorous letters, exchanges with close friends and well-known personalities; show something about the man, his non-involvement in politics, his concern over lack of public knowledge and interest in world affairs, his despair with television for not taking a stronger lead in educating people. Included are requests for appointments and invitations to speak, requests from charities and from friends for help in finding jobs and asking for personal advice, as well as inquiries pertaining to his programs and special events over the years.
Series 2 is devoted to personal matters - biographical material, family, college, chronological correspondence, awards, publicity, and Murrow's death. Murrow's professional employment, documented in Series 3, covers periods with the Institute of International Education, Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc., and the United States Information Agency. Subseries of each organization contain its own correspondence, reports, and related activities. In addition, the CBS subseries covers administration, program and business operations, correspondents, nine regularly scheduled programs as well as special programs, scripts and sponsors. This series records the history of radio and television broadcasting and as such has tremendous research value.
The collection reveals not only Murrow's demanding radio and television schedule but his extensive extra-curricular involvement with foundations, organizations and clubs; his production of albums, writings for publication, speeches; engagements accepted and engagements declined; and travels.
In addition to the papers, there are approximately 1,600 books shelved in the Murrow Memorial Room at the Fletcher School, along with Murrow memorabilia, mostly in facsimile. The oak table used by the Murrows in their London apartment during World War II, and two large black leather chairs and rug from their Pawling, New York home, can be found in the Murrow Memorial Room.
Tapes, films and phonograph records are stored in the Tufts Digital Collections and Archives at Tisch Library, to be used there by permission of the Murrow Center. CBS News is the donor of "File and Reference" prints of the two McCarthy 16mm films (March 9 and April 6, 1954) and the Murrow obituary film, "An Hour with Ed Murrow," and has agreed to donate additional Murrow films.
Biographical / Historical
Edward R. Murrow (1908-1965) was a prominent CBS broadcaster during the formative years of American radio and television news programs. Stationed in London for CBS Radio from 1937 to 1946, Murrow assembled a group of erudite correspondents who came to be known as the "Murrow Boys" and included one woman, Mary Marvin Breckinridge. Murrow's and their broadcasts from London, Europe, Africa, and Asia before and during World War II set the standard for US foreign news broadcasting. They also helped shape the public's view of a war that Americans were at first reluctant to be drawn into.
Returning to the US in 1946, Murrow became one of the most renowned radio and television news broadcasters of his time. Particularly famous were his programs Hear It Now, This I Believe, Person to Person, See It Now, and Years of Crisis. Of particular note are his 1954 broadcast about Senator Joseph McCarthy's persecution of presumed Communists and his 1960 Harvest of Shame documentary depicting the plight of migrant farm workers in the US. From 1961 to January 1964 he served as the Director of the United States Information Agency (USIA). Murrow died of cancer on April 27, 1965.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Edward R. Murrow; Radio journalists -- United States -- History -- Sources; Television journalists -- United States -- History -- Sources; Media and broadcast history
- Correspondence, 1930 -- 1965; MS025.001; 20.9 Linear Feet; 24 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into seven parts.
  001: General The general correspondence includes correspondence with admirers, personal friends, business associates, and prominent individuals such as Eleanor Roosevelt.
  002: Applicants Correspondence with applicants include papers from individuals applying for employment with Murrow at CBS.
  003: Books Correspondence relating to books contains files about books sent by publishers and authors to Murrow.
  004: Engagements Accepted Correspondence regarding engagements accepted relates to speeches given by Murrow.
  005: Engagements Declined There are also files relating to engagements declined by Murrow.
  006: Special Events Some correspondence relates to special events and is arranged chronologically.
  007: Special People Some correspondence relates to special people and is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - General correspondence, 1945 -- 1965; 1947 -- 1965; MS025.001.001; 14.85 Linear Feet
    The general correspondence includes correspondence with admirers, personal friends, business associates, and prominent individuals such as Eleanor Roosevelt. __The general correspondence files, 1945-1965, are arranged chronologically by year(s) groupings and then alphabetically by last or corporate name within each grouping. The incoming letters and outgoing replies for any particular individual or corporate name are arranged in reverse chronological order, with the most recent item appearing first.
    The general correspondence includes both important and unimportant correspondence with admirers, personal friends, business associates, and individuals of recognized importance such as Eleanor Roosevelt and U. Nu. There is correspondence asking Murrow to endorse various products. He likewise received many invitations to speak, sign petitions, attend meetings, and join organizations or boards. Murrrow received many program suggestions, many of which are accompanied by supporting documentation.
    Murrow's correspondence, 1961-63, as director of the United States Information Agency is maintained by the National Archives in Record Group 306. Some personal correspondence for this period is filed in Series 003.003.
    There is little correspondence for 1964-65, when Murrow was ill. Those letters that were answered were handled by Mrs. Murrow.
    - General correspondence, A-E, 1947 -- 1949; MS025.001.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
      Microfilm Reel 1
    - General correspondence, F-I, 1947 -- 1949; MS025.001.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    - General correspondence, J-O, 1947 -- 1949; MS025.001.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    - General correspondence, P-R, 1947 -- 1949; MS025.001.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    - General correspondence, S-T, 1945 -- 1949; MS025.001.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, U-Z, 1947 -- 1949; MS025.001.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, A-B, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, C, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
    - General correspondence, D-G, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.003.00009 (Box 3)
      Microfilm Reel 2
    - General correspondence, H-I, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.003.00010 (Box 3)
    - General correspondence, J-L, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.003.00011 (Box 3)
    - General correspondence, M-O, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.003.00012 (Box 3)
    - General correspondence, P-R, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.004.00013 (Box 4)
      Also included in this folder are correspondence from Eleanor Roosevelt to Edward R. Murrow dated 3 October 1950 and 19 May 1950. Microfilm Reel 2
    - General correspondence, S-T, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.004.00014 (Box 4)
    - General correspondence, U-Z, 1950 -- 1951; MS025.001.001.004.00015 (Box 4)
    - General correspondence, A-B, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.004.00016 (Box 4)
    - General correspondence, C, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.005.00017 (Box 5)
      Microfilm Reel 3
    - General correspondence, D-E, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.005.00018 (Box 5)
    - General correspondence, F-G, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.005.00019 (Box 5)
    - General correspondence, H-J, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.005.00020 (Box 5)
    - General correspondence, K-L, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.005.00021 (Box 5)
      Also included in this folder is a correspondence from Charles Lindbergh to Edward R. Murrow dated 29 April 1953. Microfilm Reel 3
    - General correspondence, M-O, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.006.00022 (Box 6)
    - General correspondence, P-R, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.006.00023 (Box 6)
    - General correspondence, S-T, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.006.00024 (Box 6)
    - General correspondence, U-Z, 1952 -- 1953; MS025.001.001.006.00025 (Box 6)
      Microfilm Reel 4
    - General correspondence, A-B, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.007.00026 (Box 7)
    - General correspondence, C, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.007.00027 (Box 7)
    - General correspondence, D-F, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.007.00028 (Box 7)
      Also included in this folder is a correspondence from Anthony Eden to Edward R. Murrow dated 25 November 1954. There is a correspondence from Albert Einstein to Edward R. Murrow dated 21 April 1954 as well. Microfilm Reel 4
    - General correspondence, G, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.007.00029 (Box 7)
    - General correspondence, H, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.007.00030 (Box 7)
    - General correspondence, I-J, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.008.00031 (Box 8)
    - General correspondence, K, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.008.00032 (Box 8)
      Also included in this folder is a correspondence from Helen Keller to Edward R. Murrow dated 13 March 1954. Microfilm Reel 4
    - General correspondence, L, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.008.00033 (Box 8)
    - General correspondence, M, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.008.00034 (Box 8)
    - General correspondence, N-O, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.008.00035 (Box 8)
      Also included in this folder is a correspondence from Robert Oppenheimer to Edward R. Murrow dated 30 December 1954. Microfilm Reel 5
    - General correspondence, P-R, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.009.00036 (Box 9)
      Also included in this folder are correspondence from Eleanor Roosevelt to Edward R. Murrow dated 7 March 1955, 31 March 1955, and 10 November 1955. Microfilm Reel 5
    - General correspondence, Sa-Si, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.009.00037 (Box 9)
      Microfilm Reel 5
    - General correspondence, Sk-Sz, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.009.00038 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, T, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.009.00039 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, U-V, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.009.00040 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, W, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.009.00041 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, X-Z, 1954 -- 1955; MS025.001.001.009.00042 (Box 9)
    - General correspondence, A, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.010.00043 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, B, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.010.00044 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, C, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.010.00045 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, D-F, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.010.00046 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence, G, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.011.00047 (Box 11)
      Microfilm Reel 6
    - General correspondence, H, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.011.00048 (Box 11)
    - General correspondence, I-J, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.011.00049 (Box 11)
    - General correspondence, K, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.011.00050 (Box 11)
    - General correspondence, L, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.012.00051 (Box 12)
    - General correspondence, M, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.012.00052 (Box 12)
    - General correspondence, N-O, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.012.00053 (Box 12)
    - General correspondence, P-R, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.012.00054 (Box 12)
      Also included in this folder is a correspondence from Eleanor Roosevelt to Edward R. Murrow dated 9 October 1956. Microfilm Reel 6
    - General correspondence, Sa-Si, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.013.00055 (Box 13)
    - General correspondence, Sk-Sz, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.013.00056 (Box 13)
    - General correspondence, T, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.013.00057 (Box 13)
    - General correspondence, U-V, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.013.00058 (Box 13)
    - General correspondence, Wa-Wh, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.013.00059 (Box 13)
      Microfilm Reel 7
    - General correspondence, Wi-Wy, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.013.00060 (Box 13)
    - General correspondence, X-Z, 1956 -- 1957; MS025.001.001.013.00061 (Box 13)
    - General correspondence, A, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.014.00062 (Box 14)
    - General correspondence, Ba-Be, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.014.00063 (Box 14)
    - General correspondence, Bi-Bo, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.014.00064 (Box 14)
    - General correspondence, Br-Bu, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.015.00065 (Box 15)
    - General correspondence, Ca-Ci, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.015.00066 (Box 15)
    - General correspondence, Co-Cz, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.015.00067 (Box 15)
      Microfilm Reel 8
    - General correspondence, D, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.016.00068 (Box 16)
    - General correspondence, E, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.016.00069 (Box 16)
    - General correspondence, F, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.016.00070 (Box 16)
    - General correspondence, Ga-Gl, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.016.00071 (Box 16)
    - General correspondence, Go-Gu, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.017.00072 (Box 17)
    - General correspondence, Ha-Hd, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.017.00073 (Box 17)
    - General correspondence, He-Hi, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.017.00074 (Box 17)
      Microfilm Reel 9
    - General correspondence, Ho-Hu, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.017.00075 (Box 17)
    - General correspondence, I-J, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.018.00076 (Box 18)
    - General correspondence, Ka-Ke, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.018.00077 (Box 18)
      Also included in this folder are correspondence from John F. Kennedy to Edward R. Murrow dated 28 May 1958, 10 June 1958, 2 July 1958, 30 August 1958. There is a correspondence from Helen Keller to Edward R. Murrow dated 16 April 1959 as well. Microfilm Reel 9
    - General correspondence, Ki-Ku, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.018.00078 (Box 18)
    - General correspondence, Ki-Ku, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.018.00079 (Box 18)
    - General correspondence, Li-Ly, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.019.00080 (Box 19)
    - General correspondence, Ma, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.019.00081 (Box 19)
      Also included in this folder is a correspondence from Harold Macmillan to Edward R. Murrow dated 6 June 1958. Microfilm Reel 9
    - General correspondence, Mc-Me, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.019.00082 (Box 19)
      Microfilm Reel 10
    - General correspondence, Mi-Mu, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.019.00083 (Box 19)
    - General correspondence, N, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.020.00084 (Box 20)
    - General correspondence, O, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.020.00085 (Box 20)
    - General correspondence, P, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.020.00086 (Box 20)
    - General correspondence, Q-Roc, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.020.00087 (Box 20)
    - General correspondence, Roe-Ry, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.020.00088 (Box 20)
    - General correspondence, Sa-Sc, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.021.00089 (Box 21)
    - General correspondence, Se-Si, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.021.00090 (Box 21)
    - General correspondence, Sk-Sz, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.021.00091 (Box 21)
    - General correspondence, Ta-Ter, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.021.00092 (Box 21)
    - General correspondence, Tet-Ty, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.022.00093 (Box 22)
      Microfilm Reel 11
    - General correspondence, U-V, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.022.00094 (Box 22)
    - General correspondence, Wa-Wh, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.022.00095 (Box 22)
    - General correspondence, Wi-Wy, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.022.00096 (Box 22)
    - General correspondence, X-Z, 1958 -- 1959; MS025.001.001.022.00097 (Box 22)
    - General correspondence, A, 1960; MS025.001.001.022.00098 (Box 22)
    - General correspondence, B, 1960; MS025.001.001.023.00099 (Box 23)
    - General correspondence, C, 1960; MS025.001.001.023.00100 (Box 23)
    - General correspondence, D, 1960; MS025.001.001.023.00101 (Box 23)
    - General correspondence, E, 1960; MS025.001.001.023.00102 (Box 23)
    - General correspondence, F, 1960; MS025.001.001.024.00103 (Box 24)
      Microfilm Reel 12
    - General correspondence, G, 1960; MS025.001.001.024.00104 (Box 24)
    - General correspondence, H, 1960; MS025.001.001.024.00105 (Box 24)
    - General correspondence, I, 1960; MS025.001.001.024.00106 (Box 24)
    - General correspondence, J, 1960; MS025.001.001.024.00107 (Box 24)
    - General correspondence, K, 1960; MS025.001.001.024.00108 (Box 24)
    - General correspondence, L, 1960; MS025.001.001.024.00109 (Box 24)
    - General correspondence, M, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00110 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, N, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00111 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, O, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00112 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, P, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00113 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, R, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00114 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, S, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00115 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, T, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00116 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, U, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00117 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, V, 1960; MS025.001.001.025.00118 (Box 25)
    - General correspondence, W, 1960; MS025.001.001.026.00119 (Box 26)
    - General correspondence, X-Z, 1960; MS025.001.001.026.00120 (Box 26)
    - General correspondence, A-G, 1961; MS025.001.001.026.00121 (Box 26)
    - General correspondence, H-Q, 1961; MS025.001.001.026.00122 (Box 26)
    - General correspondence, R-Z, 1961; MS025.001.001.026.00123 (Box 26)
    - General correspondence, A-Z, 1961 -- 1963; MS025.001.001.026.00124 (Box 26)
    - General correspondence, A-F, 1964; MS025.001.001.026.00125 (Box 26)
    - General correspondence, G-L, 1964; MS025.001.001.026.00126 (Box 26)
      Microfilm Reel 13
    - General correspondence, M-Z, 1964; MS025.001.001.027.00127 (Box 27)
    - General correspondence, A-Z, 1965; MS025.001.001.027.00128 (Box 27)
  - Applicants, 1947 -- 1960; MS025.001.002; 1.1 Linear Feet
    These five folders contain correspondence and related papers from individuals applying for employment with Murrow, while he was employed at CBS. The files are arranged chronologically by year(s) groupings and then alphabetically by last or corporate name within each grouping.